Hi, welcome back to Arya Nagarjuna.
This is the review class.
We've had 14 amazing classes.
We have gone through,
I think it's nine chapters,
which is a big achievement
- that's a third.
It's not a third of the amount of text,
but it's a third of the chapters,
because the chapters
have different lengths,
and these are shorter chapters.
But definitely we've done a huge piece.
It's about 20% of the whole
wisdom text of Nagarjuna
and the commentary by Choney Lama,
which is to say, the
commentary by Tsongkapa also.
And we made great progress,
we worked through it very hard.
And I thought, let's have some fun,
let's just relax.
I have seven of my friends here.
Let's just
talk about what we just studied.
And maybe it'd be fun for
you guys at home also,
to listen to us wander
around in the dark, as they say.
So here we go.
We started with chapter nine.
And that's called an investigation
about who might have been there before.
It's a weird name for a chapter.
It's an investigation
about who might have been there
before we got there, something like that.
Who might have been there before?
I'm going to show pictures
and my esteemed friends
are going to guess
what we were talking about
with that picture.
And of course, I would give you clues
because I was careful to
study it before I came.
Because I also don't remember.
So here we go.
First picture, Dr. Pachi.
Anybody want to explain
briefly what's going on?
And I'll repeat it for the recording.
Briefly, what's going on?
There's a young girl. She has a telescope.
- [Student] She goes outside.
- She goes outside.
- [Student] To look at the stars.
- To look at the stars
but before she looks at the stars,
Is she an..
- [Student] Astronomer?
- Astronomer or not?
Good, good, good.
So which came first?
The astronomer or the stars?
It's a joke, right?
- [Student] Yes.
- Yes, she came out first, Geshe-la.
- No, but she wasn't an astronomer yet.
- Why?
- She wasn't looking at stars yet.
- Wait, so she has to look at stars
before she's astronomer?
- Yes, you cannot call her an astronomer,
until she looks at the stars.
So the stars came first, right?
And then later, she became an astronomer.
So she didn't come out of
the house first, right?
See, this is a problem.
Because of the wrong way
that we look at reality,
we are always confused
about how things work.
Always. Even with just somebody
looking at something, we don't understand.
And this chapter was
specifically about the sense powers.
And how do you look at something?
How do you hear something?
How do you smell something?
How do you taste something?
How do you feel something?
Which comes first: the
object or the seeing?
When you look at a wall,
was the wall there before you looked
or did you open your eyes
and then the seeds in your mind open,
And then the wall was there to see?
So maybe it's backwards of what we think.
It's not that you open
your eyes and see a wall.
It's that you open your eyes
and make a wall, to see.
And it doesn't feel like that.
It feels like the wall was there before.
So that can apply to the
Medicine Buddha mantra, for example.
So you say the mantra,
and then you think the mantra
changes somebody's cancer
or something like that.
So the mantra comes first, right?
And then cure the cancer, right?
No. Why?
Because until you cure
cancer with some magic words,
they're not magic words.
They're not mantras.
Mantra means words of power.
Until they show their power,
they are not mantras.
So can you say the mantra
before the cancer is cured?
Can you say a mantra
Yes or no?
No, you cannot.
It's not a mantra until they get cured.
So you have to think about it.
If Nagarjuna says,
if you don't understand this point,
I don't care if you say mantras.
Maybe you get lucky and they cure somebody
because they did something
good 10,000 lifetimes ago.
But if you want the
mantra to cause the cure,
you have to understand that
the mantra is not a mantra
until the cure comes,
which means the mantra
is impossible to cause the cure.
So something else is happening here.
It's not the mantra causes the cure.
Is that your mind creates a mantra,
your mind creates a meditation session,
and then your mind creates a cancer cure.
Duck, Duck, Duck.. Not duck, duck, duck.
So don't do mantras
thinking that the mantras
are going to cure the person.
Save life. Protect life.
Help other people's life.
I saw a funny thing today.
I took a picture of it for you.
There's a new word in the corporate world.
It's called green washing,
like white washing.
So in American English,
white washing means you did something bad,
and then you're white
washing, and it looks good.
And now there's a new
word in corporate world
called green washing.
And it means you take credit
for carbon sequestering
that you didn't really do.
You see what I mean? You say,
oh look, I saved 50 trees.
And somebody says, where's the trees?
And you're like, well... (looks away),
and it's called 'green-washing' now.
It's a new verb in American industry.
Why am I talking about that?
It looks like the mantras is causing
the cancer to go away, but really
saving lives of animals, for example,
by saving the environment
and sequestering carbon,
which is a huge saving animals!
You can save a few fish.
But what if you save the
whole world's animals?
That would be cool.
Then your mantras will
work to stop cancer.
Got it?
Because the mantra comes from you,
saying the mantra come from you,
and the cure comes from you.
And it's not that saying
the mantra causes the cure.
Got it?
You have to save life
before you do the mantra
or the mantras won't work.
That's the emptiness of the mantra. Cool.
That's, by the way, how you can get a cure
before the mantra exists.
Let's go to our next picture.
By the way that was...
I'm happy that you guys
knew what picture it was.
This is a tough one, you guys ready?
Oh, I'm on the real one,
let's see here.
No, I think it's the next one...
It's a fire.
(Looking for)
Good, it's the next picture.
Now we're on chapter 10,
which was called?
If you look at the picture, you can guess,
"An Investigation of Fire and Firewood."
So now we're on the next chapter.
And I want to know how chapter 10
is connected to chapter 9, for $100.
Chapter 10 is
about fire and firewood.
Chapter 9 is about
how does the eye work.
- [Student] Chapter 10 is about ... burns.
- Yes, how does fire burn the wood?
Which is similar to...
- [Student] Is there an astronomer
before she looks at the stars?
- Yes, roughly. I'll give you 75.
Here we go.
Chapter 9 was about how
do you see an object;
how does the subject
interact with the object.
Chapter 10, if you remember,
who brought up the fire and the firewood?
- [Student] The other guy...
- The other guy.
The other guy,
he said, look, Nagarjuna,
quit overworking your mind.
Look, it's simple.
It's the same way that fire burns wood.
The way that the eye sees the wall
is the same as the fire burns the wood.
Why are you make it so complicated?
And then Nagarjuna says,
oh you don't think it's complicated
when you burn the wood with a fire?
Let me ask you some questions.
So that's why I have this picture
of people sitting and
doing what to the fire?
Looking at the fire - I
was trying to bridge you
from chapter 9 to chapter 10.
Chapter 9 is about how
do you see the wall.
Chapter 10 is what's really happening
when fire burns what?
What kind of wood?
But before the fire burns the firewood,
how can you...
- [Student] The firewood.
- Call it firewood? Duh!
Let's go to the next one.
What is the next one?
No, we're definitely
having a problem here.
You're not, guys... aren't
showing them in the same order.
Yes, they should be in the same order.
- [Student] Oh, by the chapter?
- I think the next one is still in the...
No, forget chapter numbers,
stick to the order
that finder puts them in.
No, well, I think the next
one is lighting a cigarette.
I think we're still...
- [Student] Yes, that's...
- I'm sorry, I saw a finger.
Here we go.
Now, I'll give you a clue
and you tell me what's going on here.
The flame is not touching the cigarette.
That's a clue.
Why did I choose this picture?
I'll start the conversation.
Is the fire the firewood or not?
- [Student] No.
- No, that fire acts
on the firewood, right?
So let's just confirm.
This is how you do a debate.
Let's just confirm, no problem.
We always say no problem.
Is the fire the firewood?
- [Student] No.
- No.
So the fire's acting
on the firewood, right?
So they're separate things.
You go like this in the
debate [spreads fingers].
So they're separate things, right?
Yes or no? Do they have a touch?
- [Student] No.
- No! So you can light a cigarette
by opening a lighter 10,000 miles away,
because they don't have to touch.
So I was trying to find a picture
that had a little bit of
space between the flame.
I mean, that space could
be 10 million miles,
it doesn't matter.
If the fire is not the cigarette,
then where do they touch?
Where can they touch?
Where's the point of contact
between the cigarette and the fire?
If they never touch, then you can't light
a cigarette with the fire.
If they do touch,
then there's a part of the cause
which touches the result. Am I right?
And in that case, something in the past
which is already gone can
affect something in the present.
- [Student] Definitely.
- No, it's gone.
If it's gone for a millisecond
or it's gone for a million years.
it doesn't matter.
It's gone. It can't do anything.
Something in the past
can't burn your finger
and it cannot light a cigarette.
Or else do they exist
at the same time? Hmm.
Anyway, what's the point Geshe-la?
Why are we talking about all this stuff?
Let me do my Medicine Buddha mantras,
don't hassle me.
I'm trying to say,
by the time you finish the mantra,
it's gone.
And it cannot cure cancer.
Something from a million years ago
cannot cure cancer.
And something from one
half of a second ago
cannot cure cancer
because it's gone and it doesn't exist.
And it can't touch anything,
if it's not here.
Mantras cannot cure cancer.
It can't be like that.
- Oh, Geshe-la,
I heard many stories.
People cured their cancer
by saying mantras.
- No, your mind created a person seeing...
talking a mantra.
Your mind created the sound.
Then your mind created
the cancer being caused.
If you want to cure cancer,
good, say mantras.
But first collect the karma.
What's the karma?
Sequester carbon,
save a billion animals,
save 780 billion animals,
I think ,I looked it up
something, in the world.
So if you fix the over...
what do you call it?..
overheating problem with the atmosphere?
- [Student] Climate change?
- Climate change...
Then you're going to save maybe
about 50 billion animals. Let's do that.
Then you can say mantras,
everything will happen.
All kinds of weird stuff will happen.
Geshe-la will get croissants
every five minutes.
Impossible things.
Next picture.
Is it.. What is this?
And be prepared to prove it.
What's in the picture?
- [Student] Its a  bundle of firewood.
- Yeah, why is it firewood?
- [Student] Firewood is not
firewood until it starts fire.
- Until you start a fire. Until it burns.
Therefore this cannot be firewood
because it hasn't burned yet, right?
(laughing)
Same thing, don't get confused.
By the way, we're still in what chapter?
Chapter 10, we're still
investigating firewood.
Nagarjuna spends a lot
of time on chapter 10.
It seems to be important to him.
Alright,
let's look at our next picture.
We're still in chapter 10.
And
we're talking about dependent origination.
What's the short way to
describe dependent origination?
What was the first thing Lord Buddha said,
when he taught dependent origination?
- (indistinct)
Yes, if this happens, then that happens.
He didn't say there's 12 links or the law.
Well, he didn't say that, he said
Look: if this happens, that happens.
He was probably going
like this [shows gesture]:
If this happens, that happens, get it?
That's dependent origination.
Later, they put a big name on it.
But the very first time he
explained it, it was like,
if this happens, then
that's going to happen.
It's just like what your mom used to say,
if you do this, you're
going to have that happen.
Your mom tried to teach you.
So that's cause and effect.
So what that means is: think about it.
The second thing to happen,
depends on the first
thing to happen. Got it?
If you do this, this is going to happen.
Now, if you talk about dependence,
the second thing to happen
is depending on the first thing to happen.
It's like: here's the coffee cup
and here's the handkerchief.
So this is the thing that happened,
and this is the cause.
The cause supports the result, right?
If you do this, honey, you're
going to get that, honey.
Okay, because that depends
on this, doing this.
Getting that depends on doing this. Right?
So there's a dependent relationship.
Results rest on causes. Right?
- No, by the time the result comes out,
the cause is long gone.
There's no such thing as dependence.
You can cancel all the
Sugeng's translations.
(laughing)
It's all impossible.
Why?
Because to have dependence,
that thing that happens second
have to depend on the
thing that happens first.
And if the thing that happens
first is already gone,
then there's no dependence,
just the handkerchief
falls on the floor. Got it?
All right, so that's what it really means.
So where's the dependence?
Now $100 question. Let's
go to that last picture,
the parts of the pen.
I say something is depending
on something in this picture.
I say something is depending on something
in this picture, for $100.
(indistinct chattering)
Somebody tell me what's depending on what?
- [Student] The pen is depending on table.
- I thought you'd say that.
Anybody else want to try?
- [Student] Maybe it depends on the seeds.
- Yes, good, $100 for Pachi.
Yeah, the pen depends on the seeds.
This is a trick picture.
This picture is a trick.
Geshe-la is going to say,
"Oh, what's depending on what?"
And Gyelse is going to say, "Oh
the pen depends on the table,"
and then Pachi can say,
"No, the pen is depending
on my seed." Got it?
That's all. That was a clever picture.
I guess, I don't know.
After I die, who's going to
remember what this picture is?
All right, (laughing)
Here we go next one.
Wait, man, isn't there...
And maybe I'm in the wrong place.
Let me check that one
(Murmuring)
Wow, this is really weird.
(silence)
Okay, we got the bundle of firewood,
we got the pen on the desk.
Oh, right, you're right. Okay, good.
The other guys said, look, you can see
that the fire comes from the firewood.
For example: Look,
Nagarjuna, I don't care,
if you say the fire is the firewood,
or you say the fire is
separate from the firewood.
It doesn't really matter.
If you put a match on some
dry wood, it's going to burn.
Now, I don't care what kind
of philosophy you have.
I can burn your house down. Watch me.
Then you can philosophize about it.
But anyone can see that
when you put a match
near a bunch of dry stuff, it burns.
And then Nagarjuna
replies with this picture.
What's the point of the picture?
(indistinct)
Well, I'm saying...
Why did I use colored glasses here?
(indistinct)
Yes, just because you see it
that way, it doesn't mean...
- [Student] that it's correct.
- That it's correct, yes, your eyes are...
Your equipment is broken.
That would be Nagarjuna's answer.
In fact, listen to this:
everything in the Wheel
of Life is broken. Got it?
And it took me many
years to figure that out.
If something is painted
in the Wheel of Life,
inside the wheel, inside
the edges of the wheel,
it's broken.
Everything there is effed up, everything.
So
your eyes, which are LNGA PA SKYE MCHED,
fifth link.
The buildings, empty
buildings - they are broken.
They are broken. Your eyes are broken.
Don't tell me fire burns wood
because I can see it.
Is everything pink in the world?
Is my white phone pink?
Why? Why are you saying that, Geshe-la?
Because if you have pink eyeglasses on,
it's going to look pink to you.
And you always have these eyeglasses on.
You are born with these sunglasses on.
And you will wear them
until the day they die.
You are born with a defect in your eye.
What's the famous example
about a defect in your eye?
- [Student] Cataract?
- Yes, which kind of means
you have a scratch on your eye
on your cornea.
And you think there's some -
- [Student] Hair on sink.
- Or you think there's a crack in
the porcelain. You see, get it?
And it's really just a
scratch on your eyeball.
So, according to Buddhism,
of course your mind is
misunderstanding everything.
But the problem is worse than that.
Your eyeball is broken.
You always see things the wrong way.
When you think you see
a match causing a fire
or when you think a
mantra is curing cancer,
you are...
There's a problem with your eyes.
That's not what's happening.
What's really happening Geshe-la?
You saved a bunch of animals
live by, I don't know,
planting a forest in Diamond Mountain.
Then that oxygen saved many animals.
And then you did mantras and
you can cure cancer. Got it?
That's all.
If Nagarjuna is correct,
we have to be nice to animals
and other humans as well.
All right, next one,
(singing)
(silence)
This picture is connected to this.
For $100, tell me why?
This picture is connected to this..
[Student] Fire, cook, pizza
Yes, good, $100 for the young man.
You are just self-reporting, okay,
if you don't report it's not my problem.
At what point is the pizza done?
At what point?
So there's past fire, there's future fire.
And there's the fire in the moment.
And that keeps moving, the
present moment keeps moving.
What is the perfect point?
What cooked the pizza
perfectly, by the way?
You've made dinner for
somebody else two weeks ago,
and you didn't burn it.
You made dinner for somebody two weeks ago
you didn't burn it.
Then you went to Rotten
Johnny's and bought a pizza
and it was perfect.
Why?
He found the impossible
line between undercooked
and overcooked.
Where's the line between
undercooked and overcooked?
Where does the part of the room
you walked on already
meet the part of the room
you didn't walk on already?
Because they're both gone.
One happened already.
One hasn't happened yet.
They're not there.
Where do they meet?
They can't meet anywhere,
they're not here in the room.
It's all coming from you.
When you walk through a door,
what's really happening?
[Student] Pictures...
Yes. Small picture. Bigger picture.
Tape up the doorframe. Small
picture, bigger picture,
bigger picture, bigger picture,
small picture, small picture.
I read a nice book once, Ursula Le Guin.
It's a short story. It's about
a tree that got overworked.
Why?
It's a very old tree. It's
like a 500 year old tree.
In the old days, when
people walked or had wagons,
life was bearable.
What do you mean?
Well, as they got closer
to me, I had to grow.
And then as they walked
away, I had to shrink.
And, you know, I was okay,
but now 80 miles an hour.
How the goddamn they expect me to grow
and shrink in a 1/10th of a second?
It's too stressful. The
tree was complaining about
I have to grow as they get closer
and I have to shrink really
fast as the drive away...
It's too much. It's too fast.
That's what's really
happening. Thank you tree.
Alright, here we go.
(silence)
And what's the favorite...
What do you call it?
It's not bitching, it's similar?
Geshe-la is always kvetching.
Yes, kvetching is good.
Geshe-la is always...
Geshe-la is always making some statement
regarding a turtle.
For $100 who can tell me?
What's the statement
Geshe-la likes to make about
this particular turtle?
- [Student] That, if you think that
the world is carrying... on the...
- On the back?
- [Student] (indistinct) the
turtle, then that means that
- everything inside the world
- they think how it was made is wrong.
- Good, yeah. $100 for you,
don't forget to tell my boss.
So, I don't know, 3000 years ago in India,
people believe the whole world
was being held up by a turtle.
that it was flat,
and it was being held up by a turtle.
If you misunderstand
how the whole world happened,
then you misunderstand
everything in your life.
If you misunderstand
how fire burns wood,
then you must misunderstand
mantras, for example.
You must. You have to.
And I give you a possibility.
How many people in ancient India
understood the shape of the world,
correctly? Zero, Zero.
Call it 10 million, 50 million,
I don't know how many
were alive at that time.
How many percent of them are wrong?
100%. 100%.
So, in theory, it's possible
that we are also wrong 100%.
It has happened in the past
that people had the wrong idea
about how much stuff?
Everything.
You got to say it like that: everything.
And maybe we were also wrong about
everything.
So then, if you're wrong about fires,
or you're wrong about how plants grow,
or you're wrong about how
your husband yells at you,
then maybe you're wrong about everything.
Wives are wrong more than husbands.
Can I say it Pachi? I think it's true.
Just kidding.
(laughing)
It's always the husband
in the kitchen, right?
Anyway,
just consider the possibility:
if Nagarjuna is correct in this book,
if this book is correct, then
everything you think is wrong.
And that means every action
you ever took in your life is wrong.
When you turn the switch
to turn on this light,
it was a mistake. That was
based on a misunderstanding.
When you turn the key to start your car,
you're insane.
(laughing)
You should be looking for
someone to give a ride.
Then try to start your car.
Otherwise your car
might not start someday,
which of course never happens.
Next one.
(silence)
This picture... by the way,
we're on to chapter 11.
So this is the third
chapter we've worked on.
By the way, not every class
was a separate chapters,
some classes took...
some chapters took more than one class.
But we did chapter 11.
Chapter 11 is called an
investigation of a first beginning
and a final ending to things.
Is there a first beginning
and is there a final ending to things.
When they asked Lord Buddha,
"Did the universe have...
did sansara have a beginning?
Does sansara have an end?
What did he's say?
[Student] (Indistinct)
What do you say?
Well, yeah, but then...
What was the question?
They didn't say 'is there', they said...
- [Student] Did you see?
- Yeah, is it evident to you?
MNGON PA - is it evident to you?
And so this picture
is meant to describe...
If you ask me, does everything
have a beginning?
I can answer you on two levels.
If you ask me, does
everything have a beginning?
I can answer you on two levels.
On an obvious level, I can say no,
because everything has a cause.
Therefore nothing has...
There is no beginning
to everything.
On a deeper level,
why do we think anything begins?
When did this class begin?
About 100 years ago.
When the seeds in your mind open.
This class, on a deeper level
this class had no beginning.
The class didn't start.
Your seeds opened. Got it?
Don't ask me did the class start?
Don't ask me how
long ago the class started.
Did you notice I'm not
using the timer anymore?
I don't care.
(laughing)
Don't ask me when
the class started. I don't care.
The class started when your seeds open.
You can answer your own question.
Don't ask me how many minutes went by.
That's not the answer.
That's why Buddha,
when they asked him
this question originally, he said...
What was his first
answer to this question?
LUNG MA BSTAN
Well, that means he
refused to answer.
Don't ask stupid questions.
Hey, Geshe-la,
what time did the class start?
How many minutes ago
did the the class start?
Don't ask me a stupid question.
Why is this a stupid question?
It started when your seeds opened. Got it?
Don't blame me. You created the class.
It's your problem.
If it goes on too long,
that's your fault.
Go to the bathroom and
yell at the mirror.
(laughing)
That's the DCI. Probably I have
to pay a commission to DCI now.
Okay, just kidding. What's next?
This was described as the difference
between making something out of nothing
and making something out of something.
Everything is artificial.
The world is artificial.
There is nothing real.
How much of the world is artificial?
Everything.
So is it empty?
Yes.
Does it exist?
Is it real?
Well, yeah, I mean,
go out and stand in front of a car
and tell me what happens.
It's still breaking. But in the one sense
it's not real but coming from you.
And by the way,
we are still in chapter 11;
trying to see if anything ever started
or anything ever stopped.
So, is it artificial?
Yes.
Did it happen?
No.
Did it happen from you?
Yes. Got it?
Alright, let's go to the next one.
We are now moving to chapter 12,
which I will remember,
which as I will remind you,
was an investigation of
whether pain was created by pain
or something else.
And then the title of
the chapter can be read differently.
Was the pain in
your life created by you
or by someone else?
Is the trouble in your life your fault,
or your husband's fault,
or your wife's fault?
Is the trouble in your life
created by you or by somebody else?
Or you can say, does pain cause pain
or does non-pain cause pain?
There's two ways
to read the chapter title.
And we have four possibilities.
Number one, and by the way,
these are representing
four different schools
of ancient thought, and
that's how we started this chapter.
Where does pain come from?
Number one: was pain caused by itself,
which is the Sankya position?
Did God create pain?
Second position:
is the pain caused by
something other than Michael?
When Michael touches
a cactus and gets pain,
did something outside
of Michael hurt Michael?
Yeah, you could say that.
Was it both,
both God and something else?
Jains say that.
There's a religion in
India that says that.
And then did it just happen
and nobody made it happen?
That's a position by the Charvakas,
which is a certain school
of ancient India,
who don't believe in karma.
So these are four possibilities.
We normally say pain is caused
by something other than me,
like the cactus caused...
the cactus hurt my finger.
Let's go to the next one...
Now, this is almost the
only normal argument
I allowed in this class,
in this whole course.
This one is a normal argument.
If I say to you,
the pain of this employee
is being caused by
someone else or by him?
What's your answer?
The employee is in pain.
If you've ever been an
employee in a big company,
you go through this like every day.
Who caused the trouble for the employee?
Who's hurting the employee?
Himself, that's all.
I tried to put one
normal thing in the future.
It looks like the boss
is hurting the employee.
There's two famous problems in life.
One is how your boss treats you
and one is how your spouse treats you.
There's just two. Kids are
probably a subset of spouses.
And this is so common if you've
worked in a big company,
somebody's yelling at you,
somebody's hurting you.
Who's hurting?
Is he being hurt by himself
or is he being hurt by someone else?
By himself, he's being hurt by himself.
That's easy. That was a normal question.
All right, we're on to chapter 13.
And chapter 13
was called an investigation of factors.
And what should have... the question
you should have asked yourself was,
'Why did they teach this chapter
in addition to..." which chapter?
Come on, the first chapter,
the first chapter
is called an Investigation
of Conditions,
Causes and Conditions.
And now, 13 chapters later,
they're using the same thing? Factors?
What's that all about?
It should have been named...
This chapter should have been named
"An Investigation of..."
this is a clue in the picture...
- [Student] Real and Unreal.
- Real and Unreal.
Yeah, fake and real.
Or an Investigation of Illusion.
That would be a better
name for this chapter.
It's really
an investigation of illusion.
Now, got to ask it...
I'm having trouble with this.
Let's take that one,
use that one, use the purse.
Use the purse.
Is it real or not?
Yeah, it's real but it's fake.
It's real but it's fake.
No it's fake but it's real.
I'm sorry.
- [Student] okay.
- It's fake but it's real.
What do I mean? It's a fake...
- [Student] It's an imitation.
- Yeah, it's a fake Gucci but
you can still carry
your wallet around in this.
Okay. Got it?
Fake real, no, sorry, a real fake.
Is it what it looks like?
No.
Can it work?
Yes.
Is the world what it looks like?
No.
Does it work?
Yes.
If you don't believe me,
go stand in front of a car
and tell me what happens.
Does the illusory steel in the bumper
break your illusory leg? Yes.
We're not saying nothing matters
and nothing's real.
The guy, now the other guy says,
look, do the leaves
change in the autumn?
Does the color of the leaves change
when the autumn comes?
Do leaves change from green to yellow?
Yes or no?
- [Student] Yes.
- Yes.
Were they green to start?
- [Student] Yes.
- Yes, so did they have an
identity when we started?
Were they green?
Are green leaves green?
Yes, so they have a nature, they're green.
If they didn't have a nature of green
how could they change to another color?
If green was not in them
how could they become yellow?
Got it?
That's a fair question.
If they weren't green in themselves
why do you say they turned yellow?
Now here's the next argument.
By the way, we say if they were green
they never would have changed to yellow.
That's all.
Your argument proves that you're wrong.
$100 for this one.
It's a tough one.
I'll give you a clue.
It has to do with emptiness.
- [Student] (indistinct)
- Come on. Think about it.
Did I tell you a joke about
the abbot of the monastery?
Did I tell you about that story?
- [Student] What about? (indistinct)
- No, no, it's a different thing.
I guess I forgot to tell you this story.
What's DGAG DBYE?
- [Student] (indistinct)
DGAG DBYE is the end
of the summer retreat.
So for three months in the summer
all ordained people are supposed to stay
inside mostly. Why?
- [Student] So you don't step on bugs.
So you don't step on bugs.
So, in India in the summer monosoon,
and after the monsoon,
there's millions of bugs around.
If you step anywhere
you will kill lots of animals.
Therefore, in general,
try to stay at home.
It's like virus, what
you call it?, lockdown.
In general trying to
stay at home. It's safer.
Don't go out. If you can
help it, don't go out.
That's summer retreat.
DGAG DBYE means
then you're allowed to come out,
and it's just like nowadays in Arizona,
everyone came out.
Everyone came out, that you can't get
a restaurant reservation at all
for this week. Forget it.
That's why we have to play
our own rock and roll.
So people come out. And in the monastery,
you can play games for one week.
And you can play a radio.
You can play board games.
You can play soccer. You
can play games on the board.
You can play carrom,
which is very popular.
And you can play a radio.
Now the miracle is, suddenly
everyone has a radio.
(Students laughing)
It's truly a miracle.
SO I remember the joke
I like to tell is...
I was having a little trouble
with one of the ex-abbots,
with an abbot who has
passed away since then.
We had some disagreements about
whether all the monks
deserved water or not?
And I paid for the water
system and I built it.
So anyway, this is how I
became his best friend.
I went to his room to have
a discussion with him.
It was DGAG DBYE. And
here's this very stiff abbot
sitting on the floor
sprawled out with his robes everywhere
and he's playing a board game
with one of the young monks.
And I'm like... It came out of my mouth:
ME LA CHU SHOR NA ...
Say ME LA
[Students] ME LA
Sorry, CHU LA
[Students] CHU LA
ME SHOR NA
[Students] ME SHOR NA
TE KHA DE
[Students] TE KHA DE
CHU LA
[Students] CHU LA
ME SHOR NA
[Students] ME SHO NA
DE KHA'I
[Students] TE KHA DE -  What the hell?
If water catches fire
what are we going to do?
How are you going to put
it out? You understand?
If the guy in charge of making sure
kids don't play games in the monastery
is playing a game with one of the kids,
then who am I going to call to report it?
It's him.
That really made me popular with this guy.
Why am I bringing that up?
The older you get
the more strength you have, right?
I'll give you a clue,
it's about emptiness.
- [Student](indistinct)
I better tell you or else
we'll never finish the class.
If you're a Buddhist
and if you're studying emptiness
and as you study emptiness
you have the instinct
that emptiness is coming
from its own side,
you have destroyed the only
antidote in the world.
A miseducated Buddhist
is more dangerous than anybody.
A wrongly educated Buddhist
is a truly dangerous thing.
A Buddhist using mantras
who doesn't understand
why the mantra works is dangerous.
Because they go around selling
something that doesn't work.
It's like a person who
sells fire extinguishers
that don't work.
What could be more cynical
than to sell fire extinguishers
that you know they don't work?
What could be more cruel
than to go sell 100 fire extinguishers
then the place catches on fire
and it doesn't work.
In a way, we must educate ourselves
about what emptiness really is.
Because if you come to
misunderstand emptiness
it will never work for you
and then you'll always suffer. Got it?
And same with mantras.
If the water catches fire,
if the emptiness is self-exi...,
if you think the emptiness
is self-existent,
then we have a problem.
Then we can't fix anything. Got it?
I don't know if you remember this one?
I don't remember if I
really nailed it down.
I think some of the pictures we skipped.
Right Pachi? I'm sorry.
We are in the chapter...
We're in a new chapter 14 about sansarga.
My Sanskrit expertise
went to the bathroom.
What's "sansarga"?
It means contact, contact between things.
How do things touch each other?
It feels correctly like a lot of Nagarjuna
depends on this question.
Can anything touch another thing?
I'll tell you what Nagarjuna
would say about this picture.
If you want money bad
enough to hurt someone to get it,
you cannot touch the money.
If you want money bad enough
to compete with someone else
to get the money, then
you will never touch...
The money cannot touch your hand.
Does that mean you can't hold money?
No, it just means the money is unreal.
Why?
It looks like you got it by taking it
but you didn't. You got
it by being generous.
You got it by making
a donation to Club de Oro last week.
And the money you think you stole
isn't the money you stole.
This is the money you got
because you donated last week. Got it?
She doesn't have any money in her hands.
Because she thinks it came from stealing.
But it didn't, it can't.
Next one.
What was this lesson,
do you guys remember?
- [Student] Short and tall.
- Yes, but with what context?
- [Student] Can you have
shortness without tallness?
- Yes, can you recognize...
What?
- [Student] Could you
recognize shortness...
- Yes, without a tall person.
And the Buddhist answer is?
- [Student] Yes.
- Yes, because it's coming from your mind.
- I've heard the weird explanations
by American untrained Buddhists who say,
oh Buddhism is all about...
In fact somebody wrote a book about it.
Buddhism is all about comparison,
what do you call it?
Short you can't see...
Short comes from long.
Basically it was saying that,
everything is... Dependence...
Dependent origination
means you can't recognize short
until you have long. And
that's completely false,
since Buddha never said
anything like that.
In fact the Buddha would say the opposite.
Which is what?
You can think something is long
without something which is short
because it's coming from
your mind, that's all.
It doesn't depend on two outside objects,
comparing them.
That's not where a short comes from.
Short comes from your mind.
You can have lots of shorts
without talls,
all over.
You can find those books,
it's amazing.
Next one.
I don't know if you remember
but let's go back to the easiest example.
There's a part of the path
that you walked on already,
there's a part of the path
that you didn't reach yet
and there's a part of the path between.
Does the part of the path...
By the way this chapter is about sansarga
which means contact.
Can the part of the path
that you already walked
on ever make contact
with the part of the path
that you're going to walk on?
- [Student] Yes.
- Cannot.
Unless you don't look so close.
And that's a Buddhist principle.
MA BRTAG MA DPYAD PA
without investigation, without checking.
I mean, if you're worried...
If you're trying to drive back
to Rimrock this afternoon
to get your nap on time,
and you sit there and worry about
which part of the road
did you already drive on,
you didn't drive on,
you're going to get in a car accident,
you're never going to get home.
There are appropriate times in our life
when you should just god-damn drive home
and don't worry about where you are.
You're going to get a car accident.
So it's called MA BRTAG MA DPYAD PA
Does the part of the road to the Rimrock
that I already drove on ever touched...
- did they ever intersect?
That's the point -
...ever touched the part of road
I haven't driven on yet7
Look, there's times in life
when you don't want to worry about it.
Just don't hit the traffic
in the Easter Holiday
and don't crash into anybody.
When you get home, before your nap
you can think about it.
MA BRTAG MA DPYAD PA
means, do they intersect?
Yes, if you don't look at it too closely.
If you don't look at it too closely.
Very famous Buddhist principle.
- Should I do my mantra,
or shouldn't do mantras?
- Look, relax and do your mantras.
- But they don't work!
- I know they don't work,
but they're going to work.
Just be nice to people,
and your mantra is going to work.
- Ah, okay good, I don't
have to stop my mantras.
Geshe-la never said, "don't do mantras."
Geshe-la said, "do mantras with wisdom
and then they work."
- But if I don't have wisdom
can I still do my mantras?
- Yes.
- Will it help me?
- Yes, your intention is very powerful.
Go ahead, but later try to study,
why they work, which is this book.
By the way this is the most famous book
about why mantras work.
In fact the author was
the highest
tantrika an Indian history!
Duh! Maybe there's a connection.
Eight thousand pages of books
about his ideas of tantra,
maybe he knew what he was talking about.
What's the next picture?
Tell me a story somebody.
- [Student] The real cream or...
- Yes, now tell me this story, come on,
don't make me repeat the story.
- [Student] Geshe-la
used to drive his lama.
- Yes, Geshe-la used to drive his lama.
For 20 years, every month.
- [Student] Five hundred times.
- Yes.
- [Student] Once thee stopped...
- Yes, we stopped at Howard Johnson
next to Delaware Bridge,
probably, were going to have
to put a plaque there now.
And Rinpoche would say, "Tell the lady
I don't want that artificial cream."
Meaning if it's created it's not natural.
We are creating the world.
It's very similar to powdered cream
as opposed to real cream.
Does it work? Well, that's a question.
(chuckling)
Next picture...
By the way we've moved on to chapter 15
which is called "An
Investigation of RANG BZHIN."
For a hundred bucks, Tim,
give me a nice translation
for RANG BZHIN in this case.
Which means it's not the
one you normally knew.
It's not... Oh, I almost said it for you.
It's not nature here.
I mean there's a better
word you could use.
- [Tim] (indistinct)
Well, what  in the selisf-existent nature?
Give me the word.
We found a better word
in fact I'm going to
change my translation.
- [Tim](indistinct)
- Anyway, identity.
Do things have an identity?
Do they have a natural identity?
And the first example we have is...
Somebody, explain the example to me.
Is this the last picture, by the way?
No, we still have some more.
What's happening here?
- [Student] Two husbands.
- Two ways to fall off. In the kitchen
when you're having your
argument with your husband
there's two extremes you can fall off.
First one...
which is the one that everyone falls off.
What's the most common misunderstanding
when you're having an
argument with your husband?
- [Students](indistinct)
- It's not coming from me.
I don't know what's wrong with him today.
He's hungry, he had a bad day,
there was a lot of traffic.
We make up all these reasons
why he's being mean to you.
That's one extreme.
He's coming from his own side.
Now the second extreme is only fallen into
by badly trained Buddhists.
- [Student](indistinct)
- Yes, if he's not coming from his side,
you always have to say "if",
if he's not coming from his side, then
he don't exist: maya, illusion,
he's not there at all.
If the mantra doesn't exist
the way I thought it existed,
there is no mantra.
If the mantra doesn't work
the way I thought it did
there is no mantra.
That you fell off of
both edges of the bridge.
What's the proper
attitude about the mantra?
It does work but only...
- [Student] if I loaded it
- ..,try to protect life,
if I try to protect life.
Yes, if I loaded it like a stapler.
Nice answers.
Let's go, we're almost done.
Hang in here.
The next chapter is 16.
By the way, we only get to 17
and we're done. Yཨy!
That's called "An Investigation of Bondage
and Freedom from Bondage."
Chained up and breaking the chains.
Like Schwarzenegger.
And this picture was called
removing the handcuffs from a nobody
and it means,
who is chained to what?
I'm chained to or ...
Yes, good, or my body and mind.
I'm chained to a mortal body.
As you get older it becomes serious.
When you're younger, it's okay.
But when you're later
you're like... the body's falling apart
and then you realize you're chained to it,
you cannot get away from it.
And your mind is also,
you chained to your mind,
and neither one is healthy.
They are falling apart,
and you can't get away,
your chained to it.
Then Nagarjuna says,
"No, the thing you think
you're chained to is not real."
You are chained to something you produce.
You are chained to something
you are seeing get old
because you didn't take
care of your seeds.
So just take care of your seeds,
and you won't be chained anymore.
That's freedom from bondage.
Next one, you guys.
This is chapter 17.
We reached the last chapter.
The chapter of the investigation of?
- [Student] Karma.
- Karma.
Which is a long chapter.
We spent a couple of classes on it,
two or three classes.
This represents "chetana"
and "chetayitva".
Yes, karma in the form of?
- [Student] Karma in form of intention.
-Yes, karma in the form of intention
and then what you did.
Either good or bad intention.
When Buddha taught karma,
it's interesting...
I think
that Nagarjuna first talks about karma
in the context of thinking
and doing what you thought to do.
He doesn't say ten kinds of deeds
or something like that.
He says, "All karma is divided into
what you're thinking and
what you thought to do."
Which is very... what's school?
,,LAS LAS 'JIG RTEN SNA TSOGS
SKYES, ,DE NI SEMS PA DANG DES BYAS,
- [Student] Abhidharma.
- Abhidharma.
Why is he so fixed on Abhidharma?
The other schools didn't exist yet.
No Mind-Only school yet.
No Sautrantika school yet.
He's early, this stuff is old.
This stuff is 2000 years old.
The fact that you can read it,
a hundred generations later,
that's something.
That says something about the lineage.
The lineage has been kept,
and it's very beautiful.
You normally you can't
even talk to your parents.
No, I mean multiplying
that times a hundred.
It's a miracle that we
can read this thing.
It really says something
about the lineage.
It says something about
the function of the lineage:
it kept it for 2000
years, it's unbelievable.
Two kinds of karma: thinking
and what the thinking inspires you to do.
Next one.
$100 -- somebody tell me
why this is relevant?
$100 dollars...
God, I'm giving away so much money
you guys aren't excited,
you're still like...
(snoring)
- [Student] ...the same
person walked in...
- Say it again?
- [Student] (unclear)
- That's a good guess but it's wrong.
What theme was happening in this chapter
that might be shown in this picture?
What is this picture?
What's happening?
It's a waiting room.
- [Student] Yes.
- [Student] Waiting
until the karma ripens.
Yes good, $100 for the young man.
You're getting a lot of money today.
Yes, where is the karma staying
until it ripens?
To earn the $100 now:
if the karma was...
There's two problems. If it was...
- [Student] If it was unchanging.
- If it was unchanging.
- [Student] If it was unchanging,
[Student] it wouldn't
be able to produce...
- Yes, it couldn't produce anything.
And if it was changing, if
(snapping fingers)
...if it was going
in and out of existence,
then how can it sustain...
how can it ripen?
How does karma wait until it opens?
That's a big issue.
And this helps to answer
that question, for $100.
The next picture helps
to answer the question.
CHUD MI ZA BA
$100, what's that mean?
- [Student] It says contract there.
- Yes, but what does that mean?
- [Student] It means..(indistinct)
(laughing)
- Work it out and then
you can share the money.
(laughing)
You have to have a CHUD MI ZA BA.
You have to have this contract.
What's the contract say?
Don't go away or something.
A don't go away.
A doesn't go away.
What doesn't go away?
The karma, it stays with
you until it ripens,
until it opens.
There's a contractual agreement
between you and your karma.
As soon as you do how many things?
Anything. As soon as you do anything
you get a corresponding 'don't go away.'
I forget what we call it.
As soon as you do...
As soon as you pick your nose,
you just made like ten don't go aways.
(laughing)
And they stay with you,
and they help explain why the karma,
whether it changes or it doesn't change,
it stays with you, because there's glue.
It's a glue. It's a contractual agreement
between you and your karmic seeds.
- You stick with me until you open, okay?
- Yes, okay...
- Let's write a contract.
- Okay.
You write a contract with your karmas
and they stick with you till they open.
Next picture.
Something rotten is
making something rotten.
It had to do with the first Arya truth
and the second Arya truth.
Second Arya truth has two parts.
First Arya truth is truth of suffering.
The money's going down, down, down.
(laughing)
There is two parts... karma and?
- [Student] No, sorry,
karma and negative emotions
- Yes, karma and negative emotions.
If the cause is crappy,
then the result is crappy.
If the apple is rotten then the apple pie
that you make from it
is going to taste bad.
What's that mean?
If the karma and the
negative emotions are impure,
meaning...
Good! Self-existent.
How could they make a? ..
Yes, how could they make a "pure" result?
How could you get...
How could you get a changing result
from an unchanging action?
If the action was not empty
then the action would be...
If the action had an identity
then it couldn't change.
And if it's still made a result,
life would be weird.
Then you'd have to be really super careful
because...
results would pop up
without doing anything.
And even in the normal
world they will complain
if you get...
- [Student] Watermelon.
- Watermelon. No, lettuce
growing all over the yard
which you didn't plant.
Even in the normal world
people say something's weird. Got it?
I think we have one
more picture remaining.
No, is that the last picture?
Okay, didn't we do the last thing?
Oh, we didn't do the movie picture?
Let's do it I'll explain it and
we'll call it a day.
You can make some money here.
$300, last thing, last part of the course.
Then we're are free.
Then grandpa can go home and take a nap
or have 20 meetings.
For three hundred dollars...
I'll tell you what the picture was about.
The picture was about...
Do you realize this picture was...
What do you call it?
...scripted. The picture's not real.
Somebody paid somebody to
come and stand there so
they could take a picture
of them making a movie.
So, it's all fake.
This picture is fake.
Somebody paid somebody
to pretend they were making a movie
and the movie is also pretending. Got it?
Isn't it a clever picture?
Come on, give me some credit.
Now listen, this is not a picture
of people making a movie. It's all fake.
It's somebody paid them
to come and stand there,
they took a picture,
they charged me $5 for this picture.
Because it's fake.
It's a fake picture of somebody making a
fake picture.
For $300 tell me the connection
to the last part of the
stuff that we study.
- [Student] The last?
- What's the last thing we talked about
in the last class?
- [Student] [Indistinct]
- Yes, but what was the example, come on?
- [Student] Rotten apple.
- No, it's a different apple.
Boy, that's a short retention period.
What apple were we talking
about in the last class,
at the end of the last class?
- [Student] Like they are fictions.
- Say again.
- No, what apple were we talking about?
- [Student] Influence.
- We were talking about
apple tree, apple tree.
[Students] The emanation?
- Yes, keep going, you're
going to make 300 bucks,
keep going, keep going.
There was a tree...
- [Student] There was a tree
- Emanated by?..
- [Student] Emanated by the Buddha.
- Is it the Buddha?
- [Student] No.
- It's not really Buddha
because you can't climb Buddha
and pick his tree.
-[Student] Yes.
- Then what happened,
what did the tree do?
- [Student] Made an apple.
- Apple, and what'd the apple do?
- Made a worm.
- How many real trees,
apples and worms are there?
Zero! Why is that relevant
to a discussion of karma?
You already got $300, but
somebody can help you.
Why are we talking about that?
The other guy said, look if
it's fake, it's not karma
and result. And we said, all
karmas' results are fake.
Come on, you're telling
me Buddha can emanate?
That's also fake but it's real, isn't it?
You can climb the tree.
You can eat the apple.
That's why the worm is there.
What did the tree, the apple,
and the worm represent in karma?
What's the three things going on in karma
similar to the path you haven't walked on,
similar to the path you walked on,
similar to the impossible
line between them?
Somebody does something, it continues,
and then it opens. Got it?
Cool, it's all unreal
but you can use it.
It's all unreal but you
can use it, that's all.
When you do the Medicine Buddha mantra
and you cause...
and you cure someone's cancer,
it's totally possible,
but only if it's empty.
Only if the energy of the mantra is coming
from saving life,
from respecting all life on this planet,
then you give power to the mantra.
And then the mantra can
cure somebody's cancer.
But if you don't understand
that, then the mantra's
kind of like paper house or something.
It's there but it's not... Good luck
if you want to keep the
rain out or something.
Understand that a mantra is empty,
and you have to put your karma into it
and then it will work.
So, you can't do... sit around do mantras
without trying to save the environment.
I mean that's a simple way to help
80 billion living creatures.
Right? Plant a tree. Then do your mantras.
Yay! That would be a real tree.
So thanks for coming to
the Nagarjuna course.
I'd like to thank Tim
for... I don't know, my God,
he's really a master to get things done.
I don't know how
he does all the things he does,
it's kind of... must be emanation.
And Pachi and Pau,
thank you for coming from Mexico
and helping us to film.
It makes it fun also.
It's a lot more fun for me
if I have more friends here.
Thank you Rebecca for
coming too from Los Angeles
to help around the whole thing
with your great cinematic
and photographic skills.
Thank you Venerable
Elly for driving me here
and paying all my bills,
especially my student bet bills.
Thank you Gyelse for Diamond Mountain
and for keeping this
building in good shape,
so we can have these classes here.
Thanks to everybody! And Christina Kasica
for keeping all our stomachs filled
during the filming. So
we had a great team here
and I am really grateful,
and thank you Choney Lama,
and thank you John Brady
for saving Choney Lama.
See you guys later! Yay!